<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Oida sou ta erga. Or, the divine fore-knowledge of our blessed Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, display'd in his epistles to the Churches Wherein is shewed (in way of paraphrase, and notes,) that the said epistles are a prophecy of the Church of Rome, from the beginning to the reformation. By W.G.</title>
            <author>Garrett, Walter.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G270A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833934</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833934</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38413</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42412)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38413)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1830:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Oida sou ta erga. Or, the divine fore-knowledge of our blessed Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, display'd in his epistles to the Churches Wherein is shewed (in way of paraphrase, and notes,) that the said epistles are a prophecy of the Church of Rome, from the beginning to the reformation. By W.G.</title>
                  <author>Garrett, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by L. Lichfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Jan. 1699/700 [1700]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.G. = Walter Garrett.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>With "Numb. 3." at upper right corner of title page.</note>
                  <note>First 4 words of title transliterated from Greek.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>In two columns.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:38413:1"/>
            <head>ΟΙΔΑ ΣΟΥ ΤΑ ΕΠΓΑ. <hi>Or, The Divine Fore-knowledge of our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour</hi> JESUS CHRIST, <hi>Diſplay'd in his Epiſtles to the Churches. Wherein is ſhewed (in way of Paraphraſe, and Notes,) That the ſaid Epiſtles are a Prophecy of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>from the Beginning to the Reformation.</hi> 
            </head>
            <byline>By <hi>W.G.</hi>
            </byline>
            <head type="issue_number">Numb. 3.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Shew the things that are to come hereafter, that we may know that ye are Gods,</q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſay. XLI. 23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>PREFACE.</head>
               <p>I <hi>Have brought ſuch Clear Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in my Laſt Paper, That the Epiſtles are</hi> Myſtically <hi>to be Underſtood; and ſhewn ſuch Fair Probability, That, tho' they ſpeak,</hi> ad Literam, <hi>of the Churches of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, <hi>yet</hi> in Truth <hi>they are to be expounded of the Church of</hi> Rome; <hi>that I preſume, it may now be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, I ſhould Proceed to the</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation <hi>of them, which if I can make good from that Hypotheſis, I ſhall leave but little needful to be offer'd further in its behalf. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince it is ſo well known al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, That this Prophecy calls al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt no Place or Perſon it predicts of, by its Proper Name; and ſo Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally agreed on, from the XVII. Chapter, That</hi> Rome <hi>(its Church, and Empire) are the Main Subject of the Revelation. For if</hi> Rome <hi>be not the Subject of the</hi> Epiſtles <hi>too, but</hi> Epheſus, <hi>&amp;c. as the Letter bears in hand; I ſhould think it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as Difficult an Undertaking, to bring them Fairly to the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>(which yet I hope, by God's Aſſiſtance, Unexceptionably to do;) as to interpret ſo many Verſes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in S.</hi> Paul<hi>'s Epiſtle to the</hi> Romans, <hi>as if it were a Prophecy of the Church of</hi> Epheſus, <hi>&amp;c. or of ſome other of the moſt Noted Churches. Which when I ſee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd according to the Genuine and Received Rules of Interpretation; I ſhall then begin to think my Pains but ill beſtow'd; and all that I have done in Prophecy, confuted with a Witneſs. Till then, Good Chriſtian Reader, I commend to thy peruſal, the following Expoſition of our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38413:2"/>LORD's Epistles; and hope, that by His Bleſſing, thou wilt find it to be a very Serious and Solid thing; and tending much to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing of our Saviour's Honour; the Confirming of his Goſpel; and the Edifying of his Church, in Faith, and Piety, and all Chriſtian Vertues. Which HE vouchſafe, may be the Effect of it. The Expoſition there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take, as followeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary_on_Revelation">
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>REV. II.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Unto the Angel</hi> (Rulers, and Inſpectors, together with the other Faithful) <hi>of the Church of Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> till An. 65.) <hi>write, Theſe things ſaith He, that holdeth the Seven Stars</hi> (the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and, with them, his Other Faithful,) <hi>in his Right Hand,</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting them with the Credit of Miracles; <hi>who,</hi> by his Miniſters, <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul, walketh</hi> (in an Unſettled Condition) <hi>in the midſt of the Seven Golden Candleſticks,</hi> the Churches.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>I know thy Works</hi> (at any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Time, or Place) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>even thy Labour,</hi> in Teaching, and Journey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>and thy Patience,</hi> in Enduring all things for the Elects ſake, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> II, 10. <hi>and how thou canst not Bear them which are Evil,</hi> putting the Scandalous, and Incorrigible out of the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> V. and (for as far as thy Power extends) Stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Mouths of Seducers, <hi>Tit.</hi> I, 11. <hi>And thou haſt tried them, which ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not, and haſt found them Liars,</hi> Falſe Apoſtles, and Deceitful Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 Cor. XI. 13.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>And haſt born, and haſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> worthy a Second Mention; as there are alſo Two of you, (<hi>viz. Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi>) Eminently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the Character; <hi>and for My Names ſake haſt Laboured, and haſt not Fainted;</hi> but tho' thy Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man decayeth, yet thy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man is Renewed day by day, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> IV. 1, 16.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Nevertheleſs I have ſomewhat against thee,</hi> O Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> even in this Interval: <hi>becauſe thou haſt Left thy First Love,</hi> being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd in Hot Contentions about Small Matters; and walkeſt not Charitably, as at firſt thou didſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> XIV. 1, 2, 15.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Remember therefore from whence thou art Faln, and Repent, and do thy First Works: or elſe I will come unto thee quickly,</hi> by my Servants, your Emperors, <hi>Rom.</hi> XIII. 4. <hi>and will Remove thy Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick out of its Place,</hi> putting a Sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den End to this your Interval of Tranquillity, ſignified by the Firſt Candleſtick; and will bring the <hi>Smyrnean</hi> one upon the Stage, which ſhall be a Time of great Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction; <hi>Except thou Repent,</hi> and ſo Prevent the Impending Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. NOTES. From hence it was, as is probable, That S. <hi>John,</hi> in his Epiſtles, inſiſts ſo very much upon Charity, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe he had learnt from this Viſion, How Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal the contrary Practice had prov'd to the Church.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>But this thou haſt</hi> (and it is very Obſervable in thee; as not being found in any other Interval
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38413:2"/>of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>) <hi>That thou Hatest the Deeds,</hi> and Doctrin, <hi>of the Nicolaïtans, which I alſo hate;</hi> who, under Pretence that Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age is Unbecoming a Churchman, Inhibit ſuch from having Wives; and teach them to ſet aſide thoſe they have; which will prove a Corrupt Fountain of many Hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Enormities. But Thou account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Marriage to be Honourable in All Men, <hi>Heb.</hi> XIII. 4. My Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Peter</hi> is a Married man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> IX. 5. and <hi>Paul,</hi> a Recommender of Marriage, even to Biſhops, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> III. 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> I. 6. NOTES. Becauſe no other Church is Commended for Hating the Deeds of the <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laïtans,</hi> but only <hi>Epheſus;</hi> it is manifeſt, that None of the others did Hate them: and conſequently, that by the Deeds of the <hi>Nicolaï<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> which <hi>Epheſus</hi> is Commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Hating, are meant, Not the Abominations of the <hi>Nicolaïtan</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, which all the World cries Shame of, and much more all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches; (the Hating of which therefore, would be no ſuch Commendation to the Church of <hi>Epheſus:</hi>) but, That fact of <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> himſelf, (with other like) which gave Occaſion to them; who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Churchman, parted with his Wife, upon the account of Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and Self-denial; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, becauſe we ought to Abuſe the Fleſh, that is, Fight againſt it, and not allow it any thing for Pleaſure. So Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> upon the place, out of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus,</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> But, alas! this Fair Pretence has been the Source of Maniſold Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purities; as in the <hi>Nicolaïtans,</hi> ſo alſo in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> See an Account of the Corruption of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in this kind, in a Book entituled, <hi>Le Cabinet du Roy de France;</hi> Dedicated to <hi>Henry</hi> the Third.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>He that hath an Ear,</hi> that is Capable, and Deſirous, of Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe Epiſtles; <hi>let him hear</hi> with good Attention, <hi>what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches.</hi> For it is Spiritually to be underſtood, and not as the Bare Letter ſounds. <hi>To him that Overcometh,</hi> (for ye are Now engag'd in Warfare, againſt the Enemies of your Faith) <hi>will I,</hi> for his Faithful Preaching, and Bearing the Tree of my Croſs, <hi>Gal.</hi> III. 13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> II. 24. <hi>give to Eat of the Tree of Life, which is in the midst of the Paradiſe of God,</hi> making him Partaker of my ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom. To Each Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual perſon, in the Life to come; but to the Church, at the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation alſo, <hi>Rev.</hi> XXII. 2.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. <hi>And unto the Angel of the Church of Smyrna</hi> (from An. 65. to about 310.) whoſe Biſhops, about 30 in number, had almoſt All of them the Honour of Martyrdom; <hi>Write, Theſe things ſaith the First and the Last; which was Dead, and is Alive;</hi> who is Preſent with you in All your Sufferings, and hath left you an Example, that ye ſhould follow his Steps, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> II. 21. that after Suffering ye may Live, and Reign with him, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:38413:3"/>II. 12. <hi>Rev</hi> XX. 4.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. <hi>I know thy Works, and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, and Poverty,</hi> (<hi>but thou art Rich,</hi> 2 Cor. VI. 10.) <hi>And I know the Blaſphemy,</hi> and Haughty Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, 2 <hi>King.</hi> XIX. 6, 22. <hi>of them,</hi> viz. P. <hi>Victor,</hi> (195) and P. <hi>Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> (250) againſt the other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; <hi>who ſay they are Jews, and are not; but,</hi> in this Aſpiring hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, <hi>are the</hi> very <hi>Synagogue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan;</hi> and under pretence of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Purity in Religion, and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, are indeed but Preparing the way for that Wicked one, whoſe Coming is after the working of Satan, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Theſs.</hi> II. 9. NOTES. It will be here Objected, That P. <hi>Victor,</hi> and P. <hi>Stephen,</hi> were Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs; and How then are they ſaid to be of the Synagogue of Satan? Anſw. For the ſame reaſon, that S. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf is call'd Satan by our Bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> XVI. 23. whoſe True Succeſſors the Popes have been; both as a Saint, and much more as Satan.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. But why art thou Afraid, O P. <hi>Marcellinus!</hi> (304.) <hi>Fear none of thoſe things, which THOU ſhalt ſuffer,</hi> but take heart again. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the Devil</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> your Accuſers) <hi>ſhall caſt</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ſome of you,</hi> as P. <hi>Marcellus</hi> (309,) and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of your Way, both in <hi>Rome,</hi> and elſewhere, <hi>into Priſon;</hi> not for your Hurt, but Only <hi>that ye may be Tried; and YE ſhall have Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ten days,</hi> ten Times (or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roxyſms) of Perſecution; and the Laſt, and moſt Obſervable of All, ſhall be (among you, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and your Brethren) of Ten Years Continuance. <hi>Be thou Faithful,</hi> O Church of <hi>Smyrna, unto death, and I will give thee a Crown of Life;</hi> I will ſet the Imperial Crown, (the Arbiter of Life and Death among you, <hi>Dan.</hi> V. 19.) upon the head of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> (310) your Fellow-Chriſtian. NOTES. We are not to wonder, that among all the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, the Tenth only is here Reflected on, (it being That, that <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> and <hi>Marcellus</hi> ſuffer'd in:) but we muſt take good No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that in All Prophetick De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of things, the Charact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are borrowed from the moſt Obſervable of the kind, as was in this caſe, the Tenth Perſecution. Examples are innumerable. I only here obſerve, That hence it is, that in ſetting forth the Fates of the Church before, and ſince the Reformation (to avoid alſo that Confuſion, which muſt needs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from Deſcribing a Multitude of Churches together) the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters are Drawn from the moſt Eminent Churches; to wit, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> among the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive; and that of <hi>England</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Reformed Churches. And we muſt here Note alſo, That the Perſons in this Verſe ſpoken to, are ſomewhat varied. It begins THOU, and ends THOU: but in the middle it is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and YE. Implying that the Ten Years Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation (or Perſecution) is here conſider'd as lighting not only on the <hi>Romans,</hi> but on other Churches likewiſe.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38413:3"/>
                  <p n="11">11. <hi>He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches. He that Overcometh,</hi> laying down his Life for my ſake, if he be Call'd thereto; <hi>ſhall not be hurt of the Second Death,</hi> Rev. XX. 14.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. <hi>And to the Angel of the Church in Pergamos,</hi> (310) <hi>Write, Theſe things ſaith he, which hath the Sharp Sword, with two Edges,</hi> the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Sword being now joyned with the Spiritual.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. <hi>I know thy Works, and where thou dwelleſt, even where Satan's Seat is;</hi> it being manifeſt by the Eagerneſs of all your Biſhops, in Graſping at Supremacy; that the Adverſary that Oppoſeth, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth himſelf, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> II. has ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Poſſeſſion of the See of <hi>Rome: and</hi> yet <hi>thou holdest fast my Name,</hi> art Zealous for my Honour; <hi>and hast not denied</hi> (but ſtood up ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for) <hi>MY Faith;</hi> the Faith that my Name and Honour are ſo near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intereſted in, <hi>viz.</hi> the Belief of my Divinity; no, not <hi>even in thoſe days</hi> of the <hi>Arrian</hi> Emp. <hi>Conſtantius</hi> (355) <hi>wherein Antipas</hi> [<hi>i. e.</hi> your Vice-Pope <hi>Felix</hi>] <hi>was my Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Martyr,</hi> or Witneſs of my Faith aforeſaid; <hi>who,</hi> for that Cauſe, <hi>was Slain</hi> Politically, <hi>i. e.</hi> Depos'd from his Government, <hi>among you, where Satan dwelleth.</hi> NOTES. It is well known, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> aſſign this <hi>Felix</hi> a Day in their Kalendar, as a Martyr, in the ſtricteſt ſence. For which ſee <hi>Bell. de Rom. Pont. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 9. But however, Biſhops, in this Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, are called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (living Creatures) Chap. IV. 6. and being Depos'd therefore, they are Slain. For which Political Sence of Slain, ſee <hi>Ezek.</hi> XXXVII. 9, 10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See alſo Dr. <hi>Hen. More</hi>'s Alphabet of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick Iconiſms, in the words, Reſurrection, and Slaughter. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare alſo <hi>Rev.</hi> III. 1. The Engliſh Reader is alſo to Obſerve, that the Greek word <hi>Antipas,</hi> is in Our Language, Vice (or Deputy) Pope; as <hi>Felix</hi> was. I know it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, That this <hi>Felix</hi> obtain'd the Popedom by Perjury; both his Own, and his Electors. As teſtify <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> and <hi>Faustinus,</hi> (Prieſts of <hi>Rome,</hi> and his Cotemporaries) in their Preface to their <hi>Libellus Precum.</hi> But then, 1. Theſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors were Profeſſed Parties againſt <hi>Damaſus,</hi> one of <hi>Felix</hi>'s Electors: and conſequently, oblig'd to make the worſt of his, and <hi>Felix</hi>'s caſe. 2 They affirm, That <hi>Liberius</hi> was not Reſtor'd, but upon his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to <hi>(Arrian)</hi> Treachery: and that <hi>Constantius</hi> had ſignified as much to the people of <hi>Rome.</hi> 3. But that, notwithſtanding, the people received <hi>Liberius</hi> with Joy: and thruſt out <hi>Felix</hi> out of the City with great Diſgrace. And it is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obſervable, 4. That they call the People that thus with Joy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the <hi>Arrian,</hi> and Diſgrac'd the Orthodox Biſhop (for they dare not ſay, but <hi>Felix,</hi> and his Party were Orthodox; nay, they plainly intimate they were; and that, by the very Oath they are ſaid to have taken; which was done in <hi>Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi>'s
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:38413:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>behalf, while as yet he was a ſufferer for the True Faith: they call, I ſay, this ſort of People) the Multitude of the FAITHFUL; which ſounds to me a great Sole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm, and makes me not know what to think of their Charge of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury. Which yet, if it were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo True, would not hinder, but that <hi>Felix</hi> might be afterwards Chriſt's Faithful Witneſs. For it is very hard to judge of Men's Actions Certainly, as to How they ſtand in God's Eſteem; without knowing ALL CIRCUMSTAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CES: which it is Impoſſible for Us to know.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. <hi>But I have a few things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, becauſe thou haſt there</hi> in great Eſteem, <hi>them that hold</hi> a Doctrin like <hi>the Doctrin of Baalam,</hi> Num. XXV. <hi>who taught Balak to caſt a Stumbling-block before the children of Iſrael, to eat things ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed unto Idols, and to commit Fornication;</hi> for your Great Men are now Employ'd, in Sophiſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Chriſtianity with an Admiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Heatheniſh Superſtitions; hallowing them, and bringing them into the Churches. [<hi>Baron. an.</hi> 44. to 1. <hi>art.</hi> 86. <hi>&amp; paſſim alibi. Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Myſt. In. Progr.</hi> 4.] Which Cuſtom your <hi>Balak Julian</hi> (365) takes advantage of; particularly of your Fond way of doing Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to your Emperors, by Bowing to their Images; for This, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up his Own, in the company of the gods, he makes a Stumbling-block to you. For if you Bow to That, you muſt ſeem to Worſhip the gods too. <hi>Theod. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. <hi>Symſon</hi>'s Church-Hiſtory, in <hi>Julian.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">15. <hi>So haſt thou alſo them</hi> in great Eſteem, <hi>that hold the Doctrin of the Nicolaitans,</hi> (ſee ver. 6.) <hi>which I hate,</hi> both Root and Branch; both Specious Bloſſom, and Accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Fruit.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. <hi>Repent; or elſe I will come unto thee quickly,</hi> by my Servants, both Emperors, and Preachers; <hi>and will fight againſt them,</hi> that pretend ſo vainly to this Voluntary, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commanded Continency, <hi>with the</hi> Two-edged <hi>Sword of my mouth.</hi> NOTES. The Emperors <hi>Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, Valens,</hi> and <hi>Gratian,</hi> (382) were fain to make a Law, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit all ſuch as made Profeſſion of Continency, once to ſet foot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Widow's Doors, <hi>&amp;c. lib.</hi> 20. <hi>de Epiſc. &amp; Cler. in Cod. Theodoſ.</hi> Whereupon S. <hi>Jerom</hi> (to give the Sword a Spiritual Edge too) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighs moſt Bitterly againſt the Manners of the Clergy; acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that there was but too Juſt Occaſion for ſuch a Law. <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Myſt. In. Progr.</hi> 6. <hi>Hieron. ad Euſtoch. Ep.</hi> 22. <hi>ad Nepot.</hi> 2. It plainly appeareth (ſaith <hi>Morney</hi> there) to what a Looſeneſs and Lewdneſs about Women, their Wealth had carried them, by thoſe Reproofs which S. <hi>Jerom</hi> giveth them in his Epiſtles; wherein he ſheweth, by what Infamous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices they lay at catch for Legacies and Inheritances, &amp;c. And a little before, out of <hi>Jerom;</hi> The Clerks, (ſaith <hi>Jerom</hi>) who in duty ſhould be an Awe unto them, kiſs the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38413:4"/>heads, and reaching out their hands, as if they would bleſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Reward of their Saluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For this his free ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as <hi>Morney</hi> there obſerves fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) the Clergy of <hi>Rome</hi> took him for their Enemy, and forc'd him to return to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Paulinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nola</hi> (adds <hi>Morney</hi>) was for the ſame cauſe, ſerved with the ſame Sauce; as appeareth by his firſt Epiſtle: where he ſheweth, that he could by no other means, be ſafe and free from the Contagions of that City, but by getting himſelf away far off from it. Neither doth he ſpare the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> himſelf: Thou knoweſt (ſaith <hi>Paulinus</hi>) what loſs we ſuffer of the Grace of God, by the proud Diſcretion and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Biſhop of that City. Meaning Pope <hi>Syricius;</hi> who firſt eſtabliſht the Forbiddance of Prieſts Marriages, as <hi>Morney</hi> notes. <hi>Prog.</hi> 8. But all this while Honeſt <hi>Vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> was the Man, that made the Faithfulleſt Uſe of the Spiritual Sword; who (with certain Biſhops his Conſorts) was a ſharp Reprover of the then Growing Superſtitions, of Forced Continency, which he ſtuck not to call, <hi>Libidinis Seminarium;</hi>) Veneration of Sepulcres, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics; and Celebration of Vigils, (Wakes, Nocturnal Conventions) in Honour of Martyrs: all which, he roundly Taxt as Inlets to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and Fornication, (as indeed they afterwards Prov'd;) that is, in effect, as <hi>Balaamitiſh</hi> Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Stumbling-blocks to God's People. For which ſee <hi>Hieron. adv. Vigilantium.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="17">17. <hi>He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches. To him that Overcometh,</hi> inſtead of the Dainties that your Biſhop's Tables now abound with, <hi>I will give to eat of the Hidden Manna,</hi> the True Bread, <hi>Joh.</hi> VI. whoſe Goodneſs is Hid from moſt in theſe days; <hi>And I will give him a White Stone,</hi> i.e. Abſolution and Juſtification; <hi>and in the Stone a New Name written,</hi> or, in plain Terms, I will Reform my Church, which is Now Degenerated; and they ſhall be Called Proteſtants, (and not Catholicks,) a Name that ſhall be extremely Decryed by the Adverſe Party; and <hi>which no man knoweth</hi> how to Value, <hi>ſaving he that Receiveth it,</hi> and is Sincere in his Profeſſion. NOTES. This is ſpoken with regard to the Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Councils, Debates, Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, Sentences, and Appeals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in this Interval; Decrees made <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con;</hi> Acquitting many times the Guilty, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the Innocent. Thus St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> with the Church of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi> was Unjuſtly Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Popes (424) [See <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi>'s <hi>Myſt. In. Progr.</hi> 17.] And P. <hi>Sixtus</hi> III. wrongfully accus'd of Adultery (432.) But to All ſuch perſons as are thus treated, tho' by the Higheſt Authority upon Earth, Chriſt here Promiſeth the White Stone of Abſolution, as Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring to the Caſes now mention'd.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. <hi>And unto the Angel of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38413:5"/>Church in Thyatira,</hi> (440) <hi>Write, Theſe things ſaith the Son of God,</hi> diſhonour'd by your Images, which Repreſent him as Man only; and by other Superſtitious Uſages, as Praying to Saints, and making a ſort of gods of them; <hi>who hath Eyes like unto a Flame of Fire,</hi> burning with Jealouſy, [Compare <hi>Ezek.</hi> VIII. 2, 3, 18.] <hi>and his Feet are like unto fine Braſs,</hi> his Faithful Servants will rather Chuſe the Fiery Furnace, than comply with ſuch Practices. See Notes upon Chap. I. 15.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. <hi>I know thy Works;</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) <hi>even thy</hi> Great <hi>Charity,</hi> O Emp. <hi>Tiberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> II. (577) <hi>and thy</hi> Notable <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (<hi>Service,</hi> in Preſerving the City of <hi>Rome</hi> from the Sword of Barbarians, O P. <hi>Leo,</hi> of a Deacon made Pope, (440.) and thy like Service, O <hi>Pelagius,</hi> being then but Deacon, when thou ſavedſt <hi>Rome</hi> from Slaughter, by mitiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Fury of K. <hi>Totilas,</hi> (542.) [See <hi>Procop. Bell. Goth. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 11.] <hi>and thy Patience,</hi> viz. that of the Embaſſadors of P. <hi>Hormiſda</hi> (514) that of P. <hi>John</hi> I. (523) of P. <hi>Sylve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> (536) and of P. <hi>Vigilius</hi> (537) <hi>and thy works,</hi> worthy of a Particular Mention, O P. <hi>Gregory</hi> (590) <hi>viz.</hi> thy Humility, in ſtiling thy ſelf <hi>Servus Servorum Dei;</hi> and thy Zeal, in Oppoſing the Haughty Attempts of <hi>John</hi> B. of <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> who puts in for Univerſal Biſhop, <hi>and</hi> I know <hi>the last</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Works, <hi>to be more than the First:</hi> for, in My Eſteem the Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt are the Higheſt; and the Laſt, Firſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> XIV. 11. XVIII. 14.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. <hi>Notwithstanding I have a few things against thee,</hi> O <hi>Thyatira;</hi> and particularly againſt thee, O Emperor <hi>Martianus, becauſe thou ſufferest that Woman Jezabel,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by her Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, preſiding in the General Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> where thy ſelf art Preſent (454) <hi>which calleth her ſelf a Propheteſs,</hi> pretending to Apoſtolick Authority, the very ſame with <hi>Peter</hi>'s; <hi>to Teach, and to ſeduce my Servants,</hi> throughout thy whole Empire, by Crafty Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations, to <hi>commit</hi> Spiritual <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and to eat things ſacrificed unto Idols,</hi> i. e. to introduce a kind of Heatheniſh Idolatry. For to what other purpoſe is That Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Council's, Act. 11. (<hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vianus poſt mortem vivit, Martyr pro nobis oret?</hi> (See <hi>Bellarm. de Sanct. Beat. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 19.) <hi>Flavianus,</hi> tho' Dead, is Living ſtill; let the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr Pray for us. NOTES. To this I ſhall add the words of <hi>Morney, Progr.</hi> 14. And note withal (ſaith he) to the end you may diſcern how their Doctrins crept into the Church together with their Power, that in this Age, which came to cloſe up the firſt 500 Years, came in the Invocation and Adoration of Saints and Martyrs, inſtead of the gods; the very Ground-plot of Heatheniſm, to erect the Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſtianity upon.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. <hi>And I gave her ſpace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of her Fornication,</hi> and have not Deſtroyed the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as I have Done her Empire (474)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38413:5"/>
                     <hi>but ſhe repented not;</hi> but Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and Pride, and other Vices, encreaſed in her dayly.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. <hi>Behold, I will caſt her into a Bed;</hi> by K. <hi>Totilas</hi> (542) laying cloſe Siege to her, that ſhe ſhall not gad abroad (as ſhe did to <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi>) to do miſchief; <hi>and them</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> the other Churches, both of the Eaſt, and Weſt,) <hi>that commit Adultery with her, into great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation; except they repent of their Deeds.</hi> NOTES. Theſe were moſt Miſerable Times, as all Hiſtorians witneſs.</p>
                  <p n="23">23. <hi>And I will kill her children,</hi> the Inhabitants of <hi>Rome, with Death;</hi> K. <hi>Totilas</hi> ſhall make ſuch Waſte among them, that for 40 days, or more, <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall have no man in her. [See <hi>Marcellin. Com in Chron.</hi> And of the mighty Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine raging at that Siege of <hi>Toti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las,</hi> ſee <hi>Procop. Bell. Goth. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9. &amp;c.] Nay, after 3 years he ſhall come again, and make a vaſt Slaughter of the Citizens, [<hi>Procop. Bell. Goth. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 19, 20] And I will alſo Chaſtiſe her with a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent Peſtilence (590) which ſhall be uſher'd in by another Siege from the <hi>Lombards. And All the Churches</hi> in the World, both of This, and Future Times, <hi>ſhall know, that I am</hi> the True, and Only God, <hi>He which ſearcheth the Reins and Hearts. And I will render unto every one of you, according to your Works.</hi> Notes. This mighty Judgment here threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to ALL CHURCHES, for the Puniſhment of their Manifold Superſtitions; and Hereſies, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Natures of Chriſt; and whereby he was Particularly Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour'd, but which were very Rife in theſe Days; was that of the <hi>Saracens,</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> (623.) A Judgment, which carries its Cauſe written in its Forehead; and is a Manifeſt Reproof of the Churches Idolatries, and Manifold Errors concerning the Trinity, the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of our Saviour, Celibacy, and the like; and (as it is here called) a Rendring unto them according to their Works. By this Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therefore Chriſt is ſaid to Search their Hearts; Firſt, becauſe (as it is the Nature of All Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) it put them upon Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Themſelves. And, our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, we know, is the Lord's Candle, whereby he ſearches all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Parts of the Belly, <hi>Prov.</hi> XX. 27. Secondly, Becauſe by Judging us, Chriſt Tries us, whether we will Reform, or not.</p>
                  <p n="24">24. <hi>But unto you I ſay,</hi> O P. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius</hi> (578.) P. <hi>Gregory</hi> (590.) and P. <hi>Sabinianus</hi> (604.) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>the</hi> ſmall <hi>Remnant in Thyatira,</hi> being the Laſt Popes of this Interval; who have not been carried down the Stream of your Predeceſſors Ambition: to you, I ſay, <hi>as many as have not this Doctrin</hi> I am now to ſpeak of; (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) <hi>that is, which have not known</hi> (or approved) but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned utterly, <hi>the Depths of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> (as they ſpeak) the Deep Diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation of <hi>John</hi> B. of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> who arrogantly aſſumes the title of Univerſal Biſhop (580.) and is therefore commonly and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38413:6"/>rightly ſtyl'd Satan, the Adverſary, the Oppoſer, and Exalter of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Luciſer,</hi> the Fore-runner of Anti-Chriſt. [For which ſee 2 <hi>To. Concil. in Decr. Pelag.</hi> 2. Alſo, <hi>Greg. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 36, 54 Alſo, <hi>Morn. Myſt. In. Progr.</hi> 20, 21.] <hi>I will put upon you no greater Burthen,</hi> as to this Matter: for I perceive you are not very Eaſy under it.</p>
                  <p n="25">25 <hi>But that which ye have</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, the Decrying of Univerſal Supremacy, in the BB. of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> your ſelves, or any others, <hi>hold faſt till I come,</hi> to put an end to this Interval; that ye appear not to Diſſemble with me, and to Beat down the B. of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> only to Exalt your Selves. NOTES. Hereby our Saviour inſinuates, that he Knew they did but Diſſemble; as was Plainly ſeen a little after, by <hi>Gregory</hi>'s Deteſtable Flattering of the Emperor <hi>Phocas:</hi> of which (<hi>Gregory</hi> himſelf ſoon after dying) his Succeſſor <hi>Boniface</hi> III. reapt the Fruit, in the Title of Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal Biſhop ſettled by <hi>Phocas</hi> upon the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> See <hi>Greg. l.</hi> 11. <hi>Ep.</hi> 36, 44. <hi>Morn. Myſt. Iniq. Prog.</hi> 22.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. <hi>And he that Overcometh, and keepeth, my Works</hi> (whereof the moſt Conſpicuous, and Exemplary, was my Humiliation) <hi>unto the end,</hi> he ſhall be highly Dignified. For, <hi>to him will I give power over the Nations</hi> ſubject to Anti-Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII. 15. a Power like that which is now Contended for, by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of this Age; and Unjuſtly Uſurp'd by him of the Eaſtern Church.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. <hi>And he ſhall rule them with a Rod of Iron,</hi> i. e. as my Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Vicar, <hi>Pſal.</hi> II. 9. <hi>as the Veſſels of a Potter ſhall they be broken to ſhivers,</hi> they being the ſame that are typed by the Toes of Clay, which the Fifth Monarchy, the Victor here ſpoken of, was to break in pieces, and conſume, <hi>Dan.</hi> II. 33, 41, 44. <hi>even</hi> ſuch Power will I give to the Overcomer a that time, I ſay, <hi>as I received of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> who, as the Reward of my Humbling my ſelf, has given me a Name above every Name, <hi>Phil.</hi> II. 9. has allotted me the Heathen for my Inheritance, and the Utmoſt parts of the Earth for my Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Pſal.</hi> II. 8. <hi>Dan.</hi> VII. 27.</p>
                  <p n="28">28. <hi>And I gill give him the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtar,</hi> i. e. will put My Honour upon him, who am the Day-ſpring from on high, <hi>Luk.</hi> I. 78. the True Morning-ſtar, <hi>Rev.</hi> XXII. 16. whoſe Enſign was that Star in the Eaſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> II. And of the Womb of the Morning is the Dew of my Birth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> CX. 3. Whereas he that Uſurps my Power (as does now the Biſhop in the Eaſt) is a mere Proud <hi>Lucifer;</hi> an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Satan, and an Anti-Chriſt. NOTES. Hereby alſo is inſinuated, That this vaſt Monarchy ſhould be ſettled in that Kingdom, that firſt received Chriſt, and was (as it were) the Morning ſtar to bring on the reſt. Which is ſaid to have been <hi>England,</hi> under her King (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably to the purpoſe we are ſpeaking of) called <hi>LUCIUS.</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:38413:6"/>Here is alſo an Alluſion to P. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> his ſending to Recover <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> again from Paganiſm; in which Enterprize he had Succeſs; obtaining that Morning-Star, and adding it to the Roman Dioeceſe. According to that of Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> upon the place;
<q>It is poſſible (ſays he) that the Morning ſtar here may note ſome Eminent Prince or Nation, that the Church of <hi>Thyatira</hi> ſhould propagate the Faith to.</q> Laſtly, This Morning-ſtar may be very fitly alſo referr'd to our K. <hi>Charles</hi> II. in whom our Church became compleatly Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; a Prince of ever-happy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, <hi>Rev.</hi> V. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. To which purpoſe is alſo that of <hi>Rev.</hi> XV. 2, 3. where thoſe words, <hi>Great and Marvellous are thy Works,</hi> &amp;c are Eventually Anſwer'd by the very ſame, in our preſent Service for the Father's Martyrdom. Now then, as to the Star that appear'd upon K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Birth day, I ſhall here give the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of it, in the words of Dr. <hi>Love,</hi> late Margaret-Profeſſor of Divinity in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement-Speech, <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1660.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>In illius Natalibus triginta ab hinc annis, Nova eluxit in Coelo Stella, claro die fulgens, dum ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lennes de hoe nato ſibi Filio gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias Deo Pater Pientiſſimus nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuparet. Cujus rei ipſe aderam Oculatus Teſtis. Quod etiam, in illius temporis Articulo, non ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobilis Poeta celebravit,</p>
                     <l>Dum Rex Paulinas acceſſit gratus ad aras,</l>
                     <l>Emicuit Medio lucida Stella die.</l>
                     <p>Poſtero die Sol ipſe Felipſin pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur, Stella (quam dixi) adhuc praeſulgente. Quaſi tune indican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, tune ſpondente Coelo, Patris Eclipſin non obſtituram Splendori Filii.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>That is, On his Birth-day appear'd a New Star, while the Father was giving thanks to God for the Birth of his Son. Of which I my ſelf was an Eye-witneſs. Which alſo, in that very Moment of time, was celebrated by a Poet of no mean account;</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>While grateful <hi>Charles</hi> to <hi>Paul</hi>'s was on his way,</l>
                     <l>A Star ſhone bright i' th' middle of the day.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>The next day the Sun was Eclips'd; the Star, I ſpake of, ſtill ſhining bright. As tho' Heaven did then fore-ſhew, That the Father's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe, ſhould not obſtruct the Splendor of the Son. So Dr. <hi>Love.</hi> To which we may add, That after 12 Years Exile, He was Reſtored from the Eaſt. And that He, his Brother, and our preſent Gracious Sovereign, are thoſe Kings that were to come from the Riſing of the Sun, <hi>Rev</hi> XVI 12. as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more fully, when we come to ſpeak to the Vials, if God permit.</p>
                  <p n="29">29. <hi>He that hath an ear, let him hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>REV. III. <hi>Sardis.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>And unto the Angel of the Church in Sardis,</hi> (606.) <hi>Write, Theſe things ſaith he that hath the ſeven Spirits of God, and the ſeven Stars,</hi> (that is, All the Miniſters of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38413:7"/>the Church, the Inſtruments and Delegates of the Holy Ghoſt,) at his Command; the True Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Biſhop. <hi>I know thy works,</hi> O P. <hi>Boniface</hi> III. (606.) by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of a Parricide mounted at laſt to your long Deſired Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy;) <hi>that thou haſt a Name, that thou liveſt;</hi> a Swelling Title of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) Living-creature, or Biſhop (ſee my Notes on Chap. IV. 6.) So that the whole Church is now become thy Dioeceſe; <hi>but,</hi> with Me, <hi>thou art Dead,</hi> and no Biſhop at all.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Be Watchful</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>(a Paronomaſtical Alluſion;) be as <hi>Gregory,</hi> Watchful] againſt all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations in Faith, or Diſcipline, O ye Emperors of this Interval; remembring that Notable Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warning of P. <hi>Gregory</hi>'s, If there be one called Univerſal Biſhop, then muſt the Univerſal Church go to the ground; if he, which is called Univerſal, happen to fall; [<hi>Greg. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 24. <hi>Morney Myſt. In. progr.</hi> 22.] which Saying is the more obſervable, for P. <hi>Honorius</hi> (624) his falling, ſo ſoon upon it, into the Hereſy of the <hi>Monothelites. And</hi> therefore, O ye Emperors, <hi>ſtrengthen the things that remain,</hi> the Faith of the Church, and the Power of the Empire, <hi>that are ready to die;</hi> that are, thro' the Inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Popes, the Fraud of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, and the Fury of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racens,</hi> in great danger of being Overborn. <hi>For I have not found thy works,</hi> O Emp. <hi>Heraclius,</hi> (611) <hi>Conſtans,</hi> (670) <hi>Philippicus,</hi> (713) <hi>Perfect before God;</hi> for, (which God looks much upon, to whom Ye, tho' the Greateſt of men, muſt give account, <hi>Pſal.</hi> LI. 4.) ye Deny Me to be Perfect God, and Perfect Man; Depriving Me of One of my Wills; and are juſtly called by that Name of Imperfection, <hi>Monothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites.</hi> Notes. P. <hi>Boniface</hi> his obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Title of Univerſal Biſhop, was the Greateſt Blow to the Church, that it had yet receiv'd. The Popes are thereupon Diſcard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and not lookt upon as Biſhops any longer; and All is like to run to Ruine with them. The Spirit expreſſes it by Death. The Popes are Dead: the Reſidue are ready to Die. Which, beſide the Moral, has alſo a Natural Senſe, and Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification. For <hi>Gregory,</hi> ſoon after his Baſe Flattering of <hi>Phocas,</hi> Drops. His Succeſſor <hi>Sabinian,</hi> in 5 months and 19 days (as ſome ſay) follow'd him. And <hi>Boniface</hi> (that, as is ſaid, obtain'd the Prize, the others had been ſueing for) ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd his Legitimate Epiſcopacy ſcarce 8 months; for he ſate Pope but little more. And his, and <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas</hi>'s new acquir'd Honours, were ſoon attended with a Peſtilent Air, a Barren Earth, a Frozen Sea, and a General Mortality of Men, Beaſts and Fiſhes. [<hi>Cedren. in Chron. Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Myſt. In. Progr.</hi> 22.] which the Church is here warn'd to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, or Redreſs, by Watchfulneſs, and True Repentance. And we may obſerve yet further, That the Emp. <hi>Phocas,</hi> being a Murderer, was Dead alſo, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> III. 15. And
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38413:7"/>he was alſo (as <hi>Credenus</hi> reports) an Heretick; and was ſlain by Treachery, (Chriſt came upon him as a Thief too) as All his Fellows of this Interval were, who ſuffer'd alſo in like manner. As we ſhall hear upon Verſe</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Remember therefore how thou haſt Received, and Heard, and Hold faſt, and Repeut.</hi> Or, in the Words of <hi>Gregory, Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Ep.</hi> 36. <q>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtor ut conſtanter, &amp; ſine Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicio, ſervetis ſicut Accepiſtis Eccleſias:</q> I charge you, that ye Conſtantly, and Inviolably pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Churches, as ye have received them. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>If therefore thou wilt not Watch,</hi> and take this Warning from my Servant <hi>Gregory; I will come on thee as a Thief, and thou ſhalt not know what hour I will come upon thee;</hi> but all you Emperors of this Period, who have been Tardy in your Duty (of which alſo the ſame <hi>Gregory</hi> has fore-warn'd you; who brings Me in, as ſpeaking one day to ſuch as you are, and ſaying, <q>To you have I committed my Prieſts,</q> 
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Ep.</hi> 62 &amp; 65. And again, <q>What wilt thou Anſwer before the Judgment-ſeat of God,</q> 
                     <hi>&amp;c. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Ep.</hi> 52. &amp; 64.) ſhall be brought to your Ends by ſome ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calamity. NOTES. This was verified in them all; but eſpecially in the Emp. <hi>Heraclius;</hi> who <q>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the ſudden, and great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the Dominion of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racens,</hi> gather'd a great Army, and fought againſt them; but he was Overcome in Battel, and loſt a hundred and fifty thouſand of his Army. And when he Renew'd his forces again, to fight againſt the <hi>Saracens,</hi> he found that fifty-two thouſand men of his Army Died in One Night Suddenly; as thoſe Did, who were ſlain by the Angel of God, in the Army of <hi>Sennacherib. Heraclius</hi> was ſo Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag'd with the Calamity of his Army, that he contracted Sickneſs, and Died.</q> [See <hi>Symſon</hi>'s Church-Hiſtory; out of whom I have tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd this Paſſage word for word.]</p>
                  <p n="4">4. However, <hi>Thou haſt a Few Names,</hi> or Men of Note, <hi>even in</hi> this wretched Interval of <hi>Sardis; viz</hi> the 150 Fathers of the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> (681.) <hi>which have not Defiled their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> (for there is a Particular Defilement in the Sins of the Fleſh, <hi>Jude.</hi> verſe 23.) with that Really Filthy and Polluted Doctrin of the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi> [ſee <hi>Rev.</hi> II. 6.] ſo highly Eſpous'd by the Popes; but have Condemn'd it, together with the Papal Uſurpations: <hi>and they</hi> (not Uſeleſly immur'd in Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; nor Trading up and down to <hi>Rome,</hi> for the Favours of that Court) <hi>ſhall walk</hi> about their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, <hi>with me,</hi> as under my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Care and Direction, <hi>in White,</hi> My Livery; more pure in my Account, than thoſe, who by a Feigned Continency, endeavour to Appear ſo in the Eye of the World; <hi>for they are Worthy</hi> of My Service; who have not Fear'd, by ſo Generous, and Open a Profeſſion of the Truth, to Diſoblige my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38413:8"/>tho' ſome of them were his Legats in the Council, and in his Name ſubſcrib'd the Canons ſo Diſtaſteful to him. [See <hi>Balſamon in Nomocanone.</hi> Alſo <hi>Myſt. Iniqu. Progr.</hi> 26.]</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>He that Overcometh, the ſame ſhall be clothed in White Raiment,</hi> (according as ſuch are Repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Chap. IV. 4. VII. 9. and in many other Places,) made White in the Bloud of the Lamb, Chap. VII. 14. the White Raiment of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by Faith; which ſhall be to him inſtead of Pall, and Frock, the Modiſh Garments of this Age: As witneſs, with reſpect to the Latter, no leſs than three of your Emperors, at this very time, being the End of the <hi>Sardian</hi> Interval, <hi>viz. Leontius</hi> (709.) <hi>Artemius</hi> (716.) Thruſt ino a Monaſtery; and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> (717.) Chooſing it. <hi>And I will not Blot out his Name out of the Book of Life,</hi> as the Pope (714.) is blotting the Emperor <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi>'s out of Divine Service, and out of Charters [<hi>Paul. Diac. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 34 <hi>Myſt. Iniqu. Progr.</hi> 27] for Razing of Pictures ſet up in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; <hi>but I will confeſs his Name before my Father, and before his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> let the Pope, or who will, caſt out his Name as Evil. NOTES. The Victor here, (as every where elſe in theſe Epiſtles) is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former, or the Reformers, of the Church. By whom, the Main Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of All, inſiſted on againſt the Papiſts, was that of Juſtification by Faith. Which is Here promis'd to the Victor, under the notion of White Raiment; as Before, of a White Stone, Chap. II. 17. The White Stone alluding to Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in that Age of Councils: as the White Raiment, to Honour and Reputation, in this Age of Fond and Superſtitious Habits.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>He that hath an Ear, let him hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>And unto the Angel of the Church in Philadelphia,</hi> (718) <hi>Write, Theſe things ſaith he that is Holy,</hi> and extremely offended with the Prodigious Wickedneſs of thoſe who will needs be called The Holy Church, in this Interval; <hi>he that is True,</hi> an Utter Enemy to thoſe Lying Wonders, whereby they now adays endeavour to Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their Superſtitious Practices; but eſpecially, their Novel Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins of Tranſubſtantiation, and Purgatory: <hi>He that hath the Key of David; he that Openeth, and no man Shutteth; and Shutteth, and no man Openeth:</hi> no, not the Pope him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, by whom the Emp. <hi>Leo Iſaurus</hi> (718.) and a great many more Crowned heads, have, in this Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, been Excommunicated; and (for as much as in him lay) Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of their Governments.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. <hi>I know thy Works; Behold, I have ſet before thee an Open Door,</hi> at which my People will arrive after this and another Interval, <hi>viz.</hi> that Door of Reformation, Chap. III. 20. IV. 1. <hi>and no man can Shut it,</hi> tho' the Adverſary ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it with all his Might. <hi>For thou haſt a little Strength,</hi> which I will
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38413:8"/>Improve to a Perfect Reformation; <hi>and haſt kept my Word</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment) forbidding Image-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ver. 10. <hi>and haſt not Denied My Name,</hi> nor Complied with my Adverſary therein, but haſt Own'd My Authority in deſpite of him. See <hi>Myst. Iniqu. Progr.</hi> 27. about the middle. NOTES. At this Time began thoſe Great, and Famous Buſtles about Saint, as well as I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage worſhip, (as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> has Prov'd, in his Apoſtacy of the Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Times, Part 2. Chap. 5.) made by ſeveral of the Emperors, with the Greateſt part of their Biſhops, and Peers; which laſted for about 120 years: altho' Image-worſhip bare the Name; as the ſaid Author obſerves in the ſame place.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. <hi>Behold, I will make them of the Synagogue of Satan,</hi> that Oppoſe and Exalt themſelves above all that is called God (<hi>which ſay they are Jews,</hi> [with whom Only, Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is to be had, <hi>Joh</hi> IV. 22. Infallible in All points of Religion, <hi>and are not; but do Ly;</hi> a thing That Party is wonderfully addict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to, as was Foretold of them, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> II. 9.) <hi>Behold,</hi> thou ſhalt be Emp. of <hi>Rome,</hi> O <hi>Charles,</hi> the Captain of my Witneſſes againſt Anti-Chriſt, in the Council of <hi>Frankford,</hi> (794.) and <hi>I will make them</hi> of that Party, (the Pope, and His,) <hi>to come and Worſhip before thy Feet,</hi> Adoring thee after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Ancient Princes; <hi>and to know that I have Loved thee,</hi> teſtifying That their Sentiment, by Saluting thee Unanimouſly by the Name of <hi>Charles Auguſtus</hi> Crowned of God. [See <hi>Ado Vien. in Chron. An.</hi> 798. <hi>Myſt. Iniqu. Progr.</hi> 27.] and by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonizing thee for a Saint. See Mr. <hi>Dorrington</hi>'s Account of a Journey, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 252. <hi>lin.</hi> 33.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. <hi>Becauſe thou haſt kept the Word of my Patience,</hi> the Second Commandment forbidding Image<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip, the Great Trial of my Patience, and Incentive of my Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy; <hi>I alſo will keep thee from the Hour of Temptation,</hi> and Great Affliction, that by the Practices of the Popes; Rebellions of Subjects; and Hoſtilities of the <hi>Saracens,</hi> and other Enemies, are coming on thy Empire; and ſhall terminate in many moſt Expenſive, Bloudy, Toilſom, and Fruitleſs Expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into the Holy Land (1099.) like that of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in the Day of Temptation in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: <hi>Which</hi> are the Troubles that <hi>ſhall come upon All the World, to Try them that Dwell on the Earth,</hi> who are Faſt Friends to the Earthly Synagogue of <hi>Rome;</hi> and to ſee, whether the Hardſhips they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure under the Tyranny of Anti-Chriſt, will Open their Eyes to the Acknowledging of the Truth. NOTES Commandments are call'd in the Hebrew tongue, Words, <hi>Exod.</hi> XXXIV. 28. in the Margin. Likewiſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> X. 4. So here, My Word, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. and the Word of my Patience, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. is the Second Commandment: for Violating of which, the Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in their Paſſage to the Holy Land, were Viſited with the Day of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38413:9"/>
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> XCV. to Humble them, and to Prove them, <hi>Deut.</hi> VIII. 2, 16. XXXIII. 8. as the Chriſtian Church is here, with an Hour of Temptation, upon a like Occaſion, and to a like Purpoſe; and in the Wilderneſs too, <hi>Rev.</hi> XII. 6.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. <hi>Behold, I come quickly</hi> in Judgment upon the Empire. <hi>Hold that faſt, which thou haſt,</hi> O Emp. <hi>Ludovicus Pius</hi> (815.) <hi>viz.</hi> The Right, voluntarily Conferr'd on <hi>Charles</hi> thy Father, by P. <hi>Adrian</hi> I. and P. <hi>Leo</hi> III. That no man ſhould be choſen Pope, without the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and Allowance of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. Which will be a Good Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for thee, <hi>That no man</hi> by the Inſtigation, and Authority of the Popes at any time <hi>take thy Crown,</hi> or the Crown of thy Succeſſors; a Practiſe, which they will be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually Tampering with, in this period. NOTES. This may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd alſo to the Rebellion of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> Brother's Son to <hi>Ludovicus;</hi> the Undutifulneſs of his Own Sons; and the Excommunication thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred out againſt him by his Biſhops. So ſoon came the Judgments on the Empire, here Denounc'd; and from which it ſcarce had any Reſpite af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, in all this Interval.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. <hi>Him that Overcometh,</hi> (in this Interval, ſo Remarkable for the Devotion of Building of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and Going in Pilgrimages; the Boldneſs of Excommunicating and Depoſing Emperors; and the Policy of Employing them in Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Expeditions) <hi>will I make a Pillar in the Temple of my God,</hi> the Reformed Church, (whoſe Door is that that I ſaid, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. was ſet Open before thee) <hi>and he ſhall go no more out,</hi> as Excommunicated, or as ſent on Errands by the Pope; <hi>And I will write upon him the Name of my God,</hi> (whoſe Only Servant he ſhall be, and not the Pope's;) <hi>and the Name of the City of my God, which is New Jeruſalem, which cometh down out of Heaven from my God;</hi> he ſhall be a Member of the Church, by a wonderful Providence of my God, Reform'd from the Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that it is at preſent Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread with; <hi>and I will write upon him My New Name,</hi> Proteſtant, (or Profeſſed, and Open Oppoſer of the Papal Uſurpations.) NOTES. This verſe, we ſee, is the Cloſe of this Interval; at which very Time there happen'd a Notable Difference between the Emperor <hi>Frederic</hi> I. and the <hi>Millaneſe;</hi> who having newly Rebuilt their City, would needs, (in Contempt of their Liege Lord the Emperor, and in Honour of Pope <hi>Alexander,</hi> his Open Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,) call their City by the Name of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> But the Emperor with much adoe, by Force of arms, and ſolemn Capitulation with the Citizens, obtain'd at length to have it call'd <hi>Caeſaria.</hi> To which Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention there is a very manifeſt Alluſion in the verſe we are upon, that cannot miſs our Obſervation. [See <hi>Sigon. lib.</hi> 14. <hi>de Regn. Ital. Myſt. In. Progr.</hi> 49.] We are here to note once for all, That God always Diſpenſes Rewards, and Puniſhments, not only Equally, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38413:9"/>Juſtly, with reſpect to our Merits; but Fitly alſo, and Diſcreetly, with regard to our Circumſtances. As, the Proud ſhall be Debas'd; and the Humble, Exalted; and the like. Examples are Infinite. For which reaſon, as you may Obſerve all a long, I have thought my ſelf Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to expound the Rewards of each Interval, with an Eye to the Chief things that were Tranſacted in it.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. <hi>He that hath an Ear, let him hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="14">14. <hi>And unto the Angel of the Church of the Laodiceans,</hi> (1200.) <hi>Write, Theſe things ſaith the Amen</hi> (2 Cor. I. 20.) The Only Infallible Guide; <hi>The Faithful and True Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ's</hi> of the Will and Word of God; which is now, in this Interval of Learning, about to break forth with great Luſtre, and Convincive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; who does not turn all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion into a Multitude of Empty Queſtions, Argued <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> as is the Faſhion of the Schools, who Abuſe their Talent: but Peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily, and without Fear, or Favour, or any other partial Affection, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the Truth; and, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of his Servants, (as Once in his Own,) is now about to Seal his Teſtimony with his Bloud. Who is alſo <hi>The Beginning of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God,</hi> that is, the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> IV. 11. which by his Special Favour ſhall Commence in this Interval.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. <hi>I know thy Works; That thou art neither Hot, nor Cold;</hi> neither ſo Zealous for Religion, as to Reform it thy Self; nor ſo Regardleſs of it, as Quietly to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Others to do it for thee. <hi>I would thou wert Cold,</hi> and wouldſt ſuffer Others to Promote a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; <hi>or Hot,</hi> and wouldſt ſet thy Self to work about it. NOTES. This Luke warmneſs may alſo be applied to that Indifference in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which was Viſible in the Schoolmen's way of Teaching it; who indeed would Hotly Canvaſs every Punctilio, but with Equal Zeal for Both ſides of the Cauſe; and rather in the way of Fencing, than of Fighting for the Truth. And the People too (inſtead of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Roundly dealt with to Amend their Lives, and Forſake their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,) were only Neſtled in their Sins by Pardons and Indulgences; and Principled to Believe as the Church believes, without Examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whether Right, or Wrong; or, perhaps, ſo much as knowing what the Church Believ'd. But then, in this way, theſe words, [<hi>I would thou wert Cold, or Hot,</hi>] will want a Convenient Senſe. For, I would thou wert Leſs than Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, (or no Chriſtian at all,) which ſeems to be Imported by the Cold Extreme of that ſort of Lukewarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, would ſound very Harſh. For it is one thing to ſay with S. <hi>Peter, It had been Better for them not to have known the Truth,</hi> &amp;c. which ſeems to be only a more Emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal way of Exhorting to Obedience; and another, to Wiſh they did not know it. Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> is caught
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:38413:10"/>in ſuch a Net; and therefore leaves this Paſſage to expound it ſelf.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. <hi>So then, becauſe thou art Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm, and neither Cold, nor Hot,</hi> wilt neither Suffer Others to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Abuſes, nor Do it Thy ſelf: <hi>I will</hi> e'en <hi>Spew thee out of my Mouth,</hi> and will Raiſe up a Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in thyſtead, that by their Pious and Zealous Inſtructing of my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in My Name, ſhall make Thy ways to appear Nauſeous and Loathſom to them. The times of Ignorance in the two former Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals I winked at; but your Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt the Clear Light of This, I cannot away with. NOTES. This is that Cutting off, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> denounces againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> if they Continued not in God's Goodneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> XI. 22.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. <hi>Becauſe thou,</hi> O P. <hi>Boniface</hi> VIII. (1295.) <hi>ſaiſt, I am Rich, and Encreaſed with Goods,</hi> Spiritual, and Temporal; <hi>and have need of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> inſomuch that thou haſt now ſet up a Fair, or Market, which thou calleſt a Jubilee, for the Vend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thy Wares; <hi>and Knoweſt not,</hi> (but I will make thee to know, by the Contempt that I will pour upon thee) <hi>that thou art Wretched, and Miſerable, and Poor, and Blind, and Naked;</hi> NOTES. He was Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis'd for his Inſolent Boaſting at the Opening of the Jubilee (for he was the Author of it in <hi>Rome</hi>) with being <q>Spoil'd of All his Rich Treaſures, and himſelf put upon a wanton Colt, with his Face to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Tayle, and made a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Spectacle to all the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Soon after which, he Died of Diſpleaſure, that he had Loſt his Riches, and Suſtain'd ſo great Shame. This is he, of whom it was truly ſaid, That he Entred as a Fox, Liv'd as a Lion, and Died as a Dog.</q> [<hi>Symſon Eccleſ. Hiſt. in Boniface VIII.</hi>] Where alſo he tells us, how in Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing his Jubilee, he ſhew'd himſelf the firſt day in his Pontifical Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Keys carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about him; but the ſecond day, in Royal Apparel, with a Naked Sword carried before him; and an Herauld proclaiming, <hi>Ecce Pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas Utriuſque Gladii.</hi> So Rich and Self-ſufficient is Vain Man apt to think himſelf; even when he is indeed but (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niter Aerumnoſus,</hi>) moſt notably Miſerable, and Poor, and Blind, and Naked.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. <hi>I counſel thee</hi> therefore, O Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> not to lay out your. Mony for that which does not Profit; but <hi>to Buy of Me Gold tried in the Fire,</hi> the Truth and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of My Religion, as it is now begun to be Preach'd up by my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants with a Full Cry; whom Anti-Chriſt, as many as he can lay hands on, will cauſe to be Burnt for their pains: Buy this, I ſay, of me, without Mony and without Price, <hi>that thou maiſt be</hi> Truly <hi>Rich; and</hi> Buy of Me <hi>White Raiment</hi> alſo, the Robe of My Righteouſneſs, or of Juſtification by My Merits only, <hi>Rev.</hi> VII. 14. [the Leading Article of the Reformation;] and truſt not to Indulgences, the Pope's Falſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38413:10"/>Wares, <hi>that thou maiſt be Clothed</hi> indeed, <hi>and that the Shame of thy Nakedneſs do not appear; and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oint thine Eyes with Eye-ſalve,</hi> compounded of Ingredients ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd from My Word (the True Judge of Controverſies) and not from <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Writings, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Popes (as the Mode of the School-Doctors is in theſe days) <hi>that thou maiſt ſee</hi> thy Own Way, and not ſuffer thy ſelf to be led Blind-fold by Blind Guides. Notes. That the Faith Perſecuted, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to Gold Tried in the Fire, ſee 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> I. 7. And that Burning the Profeſſors Alive, was the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Way of Trying the Faith at this time, ſee <hi>Morn. Myſt. In. Progr.</hi> 50. <hi>Sect. ult.</hi> From this time forth, (ſays he, ſpeaking to An. 1215.) nothing is more frequent than Burning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where alſo he tells us (out of <hi>Trithemius,</hi> and <hi>Godfrey,</hi>) of one <hi>Conrade,</hi> an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolick Inquiſitor, who was wont to prove Hereticks, by the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of red hot Irons.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. And be not Offended at the Barbarous Uſage, that my Servants meet with from their Adverſaries; for they are My Particular Care for all that. For, <hi>As many as I Love, I Rebuke, and Chaſten; be Zealous therefore</hi> for the Truth, tho' perſecuted; <hi>and Repent</hi> of thy Errors, giving Glory to God.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. <hi>Behold,</hi> The time of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening is now over, Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is withdrawn (1558.) and Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> entred upon the Stage; under whoſe Auſpices, by my Servants and Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c. I ſtand at the Door, and Knock;</hi> propoſing in Parliament to have it ſet Open to a Thorow Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For Encouragement where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, I Declare, That <hi>If any one hear my Voice, and Open the Door, I will come in to him, and will Sup with him,</hi> by my Church in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; which, with his Wealth, Power, and Intereſt, he ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly Defend: by my Miniſters in Particular, whom he ſhall Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely Maintain: and by My Poor Brethren (<hi>Mat.</hi> XXV. 40.) whom he ſhall Bountifully Relieve. <hi>And,</hi> upon theſe Conditions, <hi>he</hi> ſhall Sup <hi>with Me;</hi> I am Content he ſhould enjoy thoſe My Revenues, that Reverted into My Hands, upon the Diſſolution of Popiſh Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents. NOTES. When God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys an Impenitent People; his Giving the Spoil to the Victor, is Commonly call'd God's Supper, Feaſt, Sacrifice, and the like. Of which, the following Inſtances are Undeniable; which we have, <hi>Rev.</hi> XIX. 17, 18. <hi>Ezek.</hi> XXXIX. 17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Eſay.</hi> XXV. 6. XXXIV 6. <hi>Jer.</hi> XLVI. 10. <hi>Zeph.</hi> I. 7, 8. Such therefore (Doubtleſs) is the Supper, that Chriſt here promiſes the Victor, upon his Bringing in the Reformation: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, If Any one, (be he of the Clergy, or Laity) ſhall give Admiſſion to My Goſpel; he has My Conſent, upon the Terms aforeſaid, to come in for a Share in the Revenues of Demoliſht Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beys, and all other ſuch Evacuated places. And the like is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:38413:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>to hold good in All other Kingdoms and States, that either have already, or ſhall hereafter Open to Chriſt. And This, with all due Submiſſion to Better Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and greater Authorities, I take to be the Meaning of this Paſſage.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. <hi>To him that Overcometh, will I grant to ſit with Me in My Throne,</hi> as My Vicar on Earth; Supreme in Spirituals and Temporals; who am King of Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> XV. 3. and King of Kings, <hi>Rev.</hi> XVII. 14. <hi>even as I alſo Overcame, and am ſet down with my Father in His Throne,</hi> having All Power in Heaven and Earth conferr'd upon me: accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Repreſentation made of it in the Next Chapter, where the Victor is ſeated on a Throne, as Head of the Church under Chriſt. For which I muſt refer the Reader to my Latin Expoſition of that Chapter.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. <hi>He that hath an Ear, let him hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches.</hi> NOTES. It is time now to Obſerve, That in the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Every Epiſtle, it is, <hi>Thus Saith Chriſt:</hi> and the End as Conſtantly inſinuates, that it is the Spirit that Saith it. Whereby is manifeſtly Imply'd; that (not only What One Saith, the Other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth to; but that) the One's Saying, is the Other's Saying. To ſay, <hi>Thus Saith Chriſt;</hi> or, <hi>Thus Saith the Spirit;</hi> is All one. They are Different Speakers, that is, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; as is Plain from Other Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. But the Thing Spoken, is the Saying of them Both, or of Either, Indifferently: as Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Same Mind, or Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: that is, from the Same Eſſence, or Subſtance of Divinity.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>And thus, thro' the Aſſiſtance of God's Holy Spirit, I have given ſuch an Expoſition of this Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Prophecy, as no man, that Allows of any Meer Rational Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of the Writings of the Prophets, can Fairly Diſallow of: and therefore it is True. As I am ready, by the like Aſſiſtance of the Divine Grace, to Defend againſt any man, that ſhall call it in Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. And, by a Mere Rational In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, I mean Such a one, as has no other Foundation, than Scripture, Manag'd, and Appli'd by Reaſon; in Oppoſition to ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations, as are Supported by the <hi>Authority</hi> of Interpreters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended by <hi>Miracles,</hi> and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Evidences. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (for a cloſe of All;) From the Expoſition here Offer'd, let any one Judge, Whether it was not with very good Reaſon, That, in the Front of Each Epiſtle, our Saviour has made ſo Solemn a Declaration, of his KNOWLEDGE of the Churches Works.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <closer>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>L. Lichfield, Jan.</hi> 1<add>699/1709.</add>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
